

Gareth Burns

Senior Data Scientist

Technical Skills

R	10+ yrs
Data Analysis	10+ yrs
Shiny	5 yrs
RMarkdown	8 yr
Quarto	2 yr
Git	7 yr
SQL	7 yr

Management

Project Management	10+ yrs
Requirments Gathering	10+ yrs
Mentoring & Training	10+ yrs
Product Owner	5 yrs
Team Lead	4 yrs
Scientific & Coporate Comunication	10+ yrs

Summary

An award-winning Data Scientist with over 10 years of experience of successfully delivering projects in a diverse range of scientific industries and technologies. I have excellent communication skills with the ability to convey complex topics to a non-technical audience using a range of mediums and carry out horizon scanning and requirements gathering to inform road maps.

I am experienced in working with a range of stakeholders, from internal *ad hoc* data analysis, implementation of annual national biological data analysis pipelines to inform international policy to working with a complex code base (c. 20,000 lines) to develop new statistical features for a production grade software as a service (SAAS) clinical trial simulation platform.

As a qualified project manager (CAPM) I have carried out a range in Project Management duties throughout the project lifecycle in a range of Data Science projects including using AGILE methodologies. This includes success

Key Achievements

Some of the key achievements demonstrating success in multiple skills and industries

Jumping Rivers: Shiny in Production 2022

Invited Speaker

Presented on how to develop production grade Shiny applications for Data Science applications, Deployment on cloud-based computing servies and how to address issues arising.

The Effective Statistician: Mastering study design and strategy with Simulation

Expert Lecturer

Provided a lecture in carrying out code optimising for simulations to result in 1000x faster run times. Demonstrating how to carry out code Profiling and Benchmarking.

Innovate UK Project: Expansion of a clinical trial modelling and simulation platform to optimise trial design and facilitate synthetic data generation

Workpackage Leader: Software and algorithm development

Developed two production-grade (Shiny) applications to improve in the extraction and transformation of real world data for use Exploristics flagship simulation software. These applications has a bespoke API that securely communicated with KerusCloud using a single login and reduced transcribing of data.

H2020 Project: InnoVar

Work Package Leader: Synergies and Future Development

21 partner 5 million funded international project whereby I organised an annual Stakeholder Forum to gather requirements and feedback from a diverse range of stakeholders to steer the direction of project. Roadmap for the implementation of drones for the collection of field plot data.

Marketing campaign

Exploristics: Statisticians in the Pharmaceutical Industry

Developed a production grade application with a statistical game and data-driven marketing collotoral to generate brand awareness and collect contact details. Resulted in 60 conference attendees playing application with 95 supplying contact details. Social media collotoral had 250 - 400 increase from baseline metrics.

Education

2008 - 2012

Ph.D. Computational Biology

Queen's University of Belfast

Variation in the nutritive quality of Lolium as assessed by Near infrared reflectance spectroscopy

2004 - 2007

Environmental Biology B.Sc. Hons

Queen's University of Belfast

Contact

- Belfast, Northern Ireland
- ✓ true
- GABurns
- DrGarethBurns

Experience

Senior Data Scientist

Product Development Team Exploristics

Developing Exploristics flagship cloud-based (AWS) Software as a Service (SAAS) clinicial trial simulation engine (R6). This involves researching novel clinical trial design features and analysis and implementing in production grade software. Product Owner of the KerusCloud ecosystems - a collection of data tools and packages to assist in common features using simulated datasets.

Senior Data Scientist

06/2020 - 08/2021

08/2021 - Present

Sociology Department Agri-Food and Biosciences Institute

Project Leader for Plant Breeders Rights Managed a national statutory testing program (c.600 k per annum) to collect complex biological timeseries and weather data (c. 4 million datapoints collected per annum). Developed a strategy to modernise dated data collection and storage systems using novel technology and cutting edge techniques. Technical expert on multiple national and international committees covering policy, governance, and emerging technologies.

Team Lead

04/2019 - 06/2020

Data Strategy Exploristics

Leading a team of Data Scientists to develop innovatative tools and solutions for the KerusCloud ecosystem and successfully delivered all deliverables for a Innovate grant

Data Scientist

04/2016 - 04/2019

Marine Fisheries
Agri-Food and Biosciences Institute

Database co-ordinator for Northern Ireland commercial fisheries data for the purposes of reporting to international stock assessment programmes. Duties include: Coordination, collation and analysis of fisheries-independent and fisheries dependent data and meta-data from multiple sources (c. 10 million biological data points per annum). Delivery of specialist advice to international technical and scientific committees. Automation of analysis and reports (R Markdown) ensuring reproducible research.

PhD Candiate

04/2008 - 04/2012

School of Biological Sciences Queen's University of Belfast

Development of predictive calibration models to assess the nutritive quality of perennial ryegrass. This involved data collection of 15,000 biolgical samples each wth 692 data points from wet labortatory analysis. Model development involved pre-processing, feature selection and validation. The calibration models were commercially used for a national forage evaluation scheme.